<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc submissionType="IETF" docName="draft-green-tls-static-dh-in-tls13-00" category="info"><?rfc compact="yes"?>
	<?rfc text-list-symbols="o*+-"?>
	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
	<?rfc symrefs="no"?>
	<?rfc strict="yes"?>
	<front>
	<title abbrev="Data Center use of Static Diffie-Hellman">Data Center use of Static Diffie-Hellman in TLS 1.3</title>
	<author fullname="Matthew Green" initials="M." surname="Green">
	<organization>Cryptography Engineering LLC</organization>
	<address><postal><street>4506 Roland Ave</street>
	<street>Baltimore, MD  21210</street>
	<street>USA</street>
	</postal>
	<email>mgreen@cryptographyengineering.com</email>
	</address>
	</author>

	<date day="31" month="October" year="2016"/>
	<abstract><t>
   Unlike earlier versions of TLS, current drafts of TLS 1.3 have
   instead adopted ephemeral-mode Diffie-Hellman and elliptic-curve
   Diffie-Hellman as the primary cryptographic key exchange mechanism
   used in TLS. This document describes an optional configuration for
   TLS servers that allows for the use of a static Diffie-Hellman secret
   for all TLS connections made to the server. Passive monitoring of TLS
   connections can be enabled by installing a corresponding copy of this
   key in each monitoring device.</t>

	</abstract>
	</front>

	<middle>
	<section title="Introduction" anchor="section-1"><t>
   Unlike earlier versions of TLS, current drafts of TLS 1.3 [draft-ietf-tls-tls13-18] do not provide support for the RSA handshake --
   and have instead adopted ephemeral-mode Diffie-Hellman and elliptic-
   curve Diffie-Hellman as the primary cryptographic key exchange
   mechanism used in TLS.</t>

	<t>
   While ephemeral (EC) Diffie-Hellman is in nearly all ways an
   improvement over the TLS RSA handshake, it has a limitation in
   certain enterprise settings. Specifically, the use of ephemeral (PFS)
   ciphersuites is not compatible with enterprise network monitoring
   tools such as Intrusion Detection Systems (IDS) that must passively
   monitor intranet TLS connections made to endpoints under the
   enterprise's control. This includes TLS connections made from
   enterprise load balancers at the edge of the enterprise network to
   internal enterprise TLS servers. It does not include TLS connections
   traveling over the external Internet.</t>

	<t>
   Such monitoring is ubiquitous and indispensable in some industries,
   and loss of this capability may slow adoption of TLS 1.3.</t>

	<t>
   This document describes an optional configuration for TLS servers
   that allows for the use of a static Diffie-Hellman secret for all TLS
   connections made to the server. Passive monitoring of TLS connections
   can be enabled by installing a corresponding copy of this key in each
   monitoring device.</t>

	<t>
   An advantage of this proposal is that it can be implemented using
   software modifications to the TLS server only, without the need to
   make changes to TLS client implementations.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Summary of the existing Diffie-Hellman handshake" anchor="section-2"><t>
   In TLS 1.3, servers exchange keys using two primary modes, Ephemeral
   Diffie-Hellman (DHE) and Elliptic Curve Ephemeral Diffie-Hellman
   (ECDHE). In a simplified view of the full handshake, the following
   steps occur:</t>

	<t><list style="empty" hangIndent="3">
	<t><list style="numbers"><?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
	<t>The client generates an ephemeral public and private key,
         and transmits the public key within a "key_share" message,
         along with a random nonce (ClientHello.random).</t>

	<t>The server generates an ephemeral public and private key,
         and transmits the public key within a "key_share" message,
         along with a random nonce (ServerHello.random).</t>

	<t>The two parties now calculate a shared (EC) Diffie-Hellman
         secret by combining the other party's ephemeral public key
         with their own ephemeral secret.</t>

	<t>A series of traffic and handshake keys is derived by
         combining this shared secret with various inputs from the
         handshake, including the ClientHello.random and
         ServerHello.random.</t>

	<t>Data encryption is performed using these keys.</t>

	<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
	</list>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Using static (EC) Diffie-Hellman on the server" anchor="section-3"><t>
   The proposal embodied in this draft modifies the standard TLS
   handshake summarized above in the following ways.</t>

	<t>
   First, for each elliptic curve (and FF-DH parameter length) supported
   by the server, the server is provisioned with a random static (EC)
   Diffie- Hellman private key. This key is generated at server
   installation, and is rotated at periodic intervals appropriate for
   any long-term server key. These keys could also be generated at a
   central key management server and distributed (in a secure encrypted
   form) to many endpoint servers.</t>

	<t>
   The static secret key is used to derive a fixed, static (EC) Diffie-
   Hellman public key.</t>

	<t>
   All steps of the original handshake proceed as above, with the
   following modification to server behavior. Step (2) proceeds as
   follows:</t>

	<t><list style="empty" hangIndent="3">
	<t><list style="numbers"><t>The server transmits the static public key within a "key_share"
         message, along with a random nonce (ServerHello.random).</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Security considerations" anchor="section-4"><t>
   We now consider the security implications of the change described
   above:</t>

	<t><list style="letters"><t>The shift from fully-ephemeral (EC) Diffie-Hellman to partially
      static Diffie-Hellman affects the security properties offered by
      the TLS 1.3 handshake by eliminating the Perfect Forward Secrecy
      (PFS) property provided by the server. If a server is compromised
      and the private key is stolen, then an attacker who observes any
      TLS handshake (even one that occurred prior to the compromise)
      will be able to recover traffic encryption keys and will be able
      to decrypt traffic.<list style="hanging" hangIndent="3"><t hangText="ii. As long as the server static secret key is not compromised, the">
	<vspace blankLines="0"/>
	resulting protocol will provide strong cryptographic security, as
      long as the Diffie-Hellman parameters (e.g., finite-field group or
      elliptic curve) are correctly generated and provide security at a
      sufficient cryptographic security level.
	</t>

	<t hangText="iii. Replay attacks are prevented due to the fact that the server">
	<vspace blankLines="0"/>
	generates a unique 32-byte ServerHello.random field using a strong
      random number generator, and this value is included in the traffic
      key derivation procedure.
	</t>

	<t hangText="iv. A flaw in the generation of finite-field Diffie-Hellman">
	<vspace blankLines="0"/>
	parameters or the use of an insecure implementation could leak
      some bits of the static secret key over time. This risk is not
      present in ephemeral DH implementations. Implementers should use
      care to avoid such pitfalls.
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	</list>
	</t>

	<t>
   Thus the modification described in <xref target="section-4"/> represents a deliberate
   weakening of some security properties. Implementers who choose to
   include this capability should carefully consider the risks to their
   infrastructure of using a handshake without PFS. Static secret keys
   should be rotated regularly.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="section-5"><t>
   This document contains no actions for IANA.</t>

	</section>

	<section title="Acknowledgements" anchor="section-6"><t>
   This modification to TLS was initially suggested by Hugo Krawczyk.</t>

	</section>

	</middle>

	<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
	<reference><front>
	</front>

	</reference>
	</references>
	</back>

	</rfc>
	
